Okay, let's meditate. Okay.
Turn off your phone
and blow your nose at the same time.
It worked.
Ready?
We blow for a few minutes.
Okay, here we go.
Then relax your forehead.
Relax the corners of your mouth.
Relax your hands.
Relax your shoulders.
Pull in your stomach a little bit.
Then come to your breath.
Watch your breath.
Then think back on things that you did
today
since you woke up
up to now.
And just go back to the day and there's
not big things. It's not like you had a
big event in your life or something, but
many small things, many small memories.
Each time you remember doing something
or saying something,
each small thing that you did today,
is it going to help you when you die or
not?
You know, was it
a good thing to do?
Will it help you die?
Or
or will it not help me die?
And divine.
Somebody owes me $50 over there.
I'll collect it afterwards.
Divide all the stuff that happened today
into two parts.
You know, these things help me when I
die.
And these things don't help me.
Life is not all big things. Life is all
small things.
Small
things you said, small things you did.
Now think about other things you did
which will help you next life, help
after you die.
And think about how your old friends
would think about these things. Oh, I
did a death meditation this morning.
Then
your old friends in your old life,
they will think that's pretty stupid
or that's depressing or
that's pretty morbid. That's a sad thing
to think about. Why are you meditating
on death?
Or today I made tormas,
little red
cakes to give to the spirits
so I will have a good retreat.
And think about how your old friends or
maybe some of your family,
that little red cake looks looks so
stupid to them and it looks like a
foolish thing
to sit in the desert
and make little red cakes, put them
outside on rocks and
it seems very
naive or
foolish.
Superstitious.
And sitting and meditating quietly
doesn't
achieve anything.
Doesn't do anything.
It doesn't make anything.
Then
try to feel that
conflict
between the way most people think and
these activities, meditating,
thinking about death,
trying to have a quiet retreat,
making tormas.
Feel the tension
between these activities and
what most of the world thinks is
valuable.
And try to get it clear in your mind
that these are more important. These
will help you after you die.
And most of the things that other people
are doing, they seem to be
pretty useless.
Collect money,
build house,
and then you die
and
the money goes away.
The house gets
sold to somebody else. Somebody else
moves into the house.
It seems from the Dharma side,
it's foolish to collect money and
house and things
if you have to lose them.
Everybody has to do his time.
So, maybe those people are crazy and
maybe you're not crazy.
And just think about it.
Most of the things you do for your next
life are they look crazy to other
people.
And most of the things that other people
do seem to be
hopeless,
waste of time.
And make it clear in your mind
what's more important for you.
This is the next meditation.
We'll spend 10 minutes here.
Be uncatchable.
Don't let people talk you out of it.
Don't regret the decisions you made to
practice Dharma.
And keep that
determination by your side.
Then, please come back to your breath.
Three slow breaths.
Then, slowly open your eyes.
Take a seat. You're doing very good.
Very nice meditation.
I think you're getting better. I I know.
Maybe you're just sleepy.
But I think you're doing better.
Somebody lose lose their keys?
All right.
Uh
I don't know. I fly on airplanes a lot
and uh
I'm often looking at what the people
next to me are doing.
And
on a normal airplane
about if there are six people around me,
maybe four of them are watching movies.
They have on the plane, but they also
carry their own movie on their computer.
And then um
it's surprising. I I fly in business
class a lot and the and the businessmen
are playing games on their computer.
And I was sort of surprised, you know,
I'm like, "When do they have time to do
business, you know?"
And they're they're paying like $10,000
for a their ticket and they're playing
games for for hours and hours, like
stupid games that kids play.
And uh
then a few people are doing are reading
books like
monster books and
weird books, you know.
People kill each other in the books and
stuff like that. And then uh
And then a few people get drunk.
Cuz in the business class they give you
all the alcohol you want
for free. And uh
Then sometimes I feel like I'm in the
wrong plane or
you know, I just feel weird. I feel like
either I'm weird or they're weird, you
know? One of us is weird.
And I I feel like I'm strange stranger
in my own country. Like I feel like uh
I I can't understand or I don't relate
to all the people around me.
And uh
I think that's a bad habit, you know? We
don't know what they're doing. Maybe
they just meditated for 6 weeks
and their llama said, "Take a break,
watch a movie."
You know? Or you know, I think you have
to be really careful about the tension
between yourself and other people. You
know, it's easy to say, "I'm a Dharma
practitioner and all these people are
crazy."
But we don't really know, you know?
Every once in a while
one of those people will turn to me and
say, "You know,
I saw angel yesterday." You know? And
I'm like, "What? You've been playing
crossword puzzles for 3 hours."
And you know, and you just don't know.
Everybody has had
mystical experiences. Some people talk
about it.
Some people give DCI talks about it.
And some people just don't talk about
it, but they had lots of them. They met
lots of angels, you know? So we don't
know.
So I think it's important.
You know, it seems like
most people are crazy
and they're just
in in Shantideva calls it mahe mahedanne
dopashin means uh
they're like sheep waiting outside of
the butcher house and they're just
getting killed one by one.
And nobody gets scared and nobody
is alarmed, you know? One sheep goes in
get killed, the next one's like, "Bah."
You know, and then the next one goes in
and gets killed and and they seem crazy.
But uh we don't know.
So just in my own life
uh when I was younger
I decided everybody else was crazy.
But when I got older, when you get 60
you get smart.
And uh
I decided maybe other people are
something special's happening to them. I
don't know.
You know, so I think it's better to In
English we say reserve judgment, like
don't try to guess
if this person is playing crossword
puzzle or
or they're Manjushri or Amitabha. I
don't know, okay? But I know I can't
waste my time, you know?
I shouldn't waste my time.
Okay? So be careful with that
meditation. That's the three diamonds,
right?
So people criticize you or it seems like
they're doing other things
useless things, things that hurt them.
But but we don't know,
okay? They could be some llama or
something, we don't know, okay?
So there's a tension, but let it be on
your side, you know? Watch your own
life.
Don't waste your time, okay?
Every time I want to take a rest, I
think
uh
All right, I feel a little tired, like I
don't want to read Dharma right now or I
don't want to meditate right now. And
then I think, "Well,
are you sure you're going to feel better
tomorrow?
Like maybe you're going to get sick, you
know?
Like
your body will get older, you you won't
be able to meditate. You won't be able
to sit. You have to lie down or your
back hurts all the time.
So if your back hurts a little, you
should meditate.
Because later it's going to hurt all the
time.
Okay? So
just do it, okay? All right.
Uh we're going back to the text. We're
doing really well on the text. Uh
Mr. Adam, you ready? Uh
yeah, nice, okay.
Den pecha le pecha means uh
pecha rinpoche bumpa and it's an ancient
book from about a thousand years ago.
Pecha means
the author whose name was Potala Rinchen
Zangpo.
He uses uh normal things in the world to
explain Dharma, okay?
So Pabongka Rinpoche quotes it.
Uh gomotentsa wadon de. So the
spelling's all wrong in in our text,
okay? It's all wrong.
It should be the LBA should be a W A.
And the S P R E should be S B R E, okay?
And uh so it's hard to translate
something when it's all spelled wrong.
Uh
And it means
the swan and the fox and the weasel,
okay?
So fox and weasel are two small
creatures like this, long tail, red
color.
They like to eat birds' eggs and things
like that.
And
this book is a thousand years old and I
never saw anybody try to explain it.
And I found it while you were doing
tormas.
But I didn't have time to figure it out
yet cuz it's spelled wrong also. The
explanation is also spelled wrong.
Pabongka Rinpoche doesn't explain it,
but he says it's an example for
uh
people who are really people in Los
Angeles,
they like to talk about roads.
You know, like if you go to Los Angeles
and you sit you sit down with somebody
for dinner, they'll say, "I was going to
take the 417, but I took the 38. I saved
16 minutes. I couldn't believe it." And
the other person say, "Yeah, I was going
over to the valley and I got the third
lane to the left, can you believe it?"
You know, and and they just talk about
roads, you know?
And they think it's really interesting,
you know?
And uh
then medong
temba temba means uh
temba means the door What do you call
that piece of wood?
The threshold of the door is called a
temba, okay? And John Brady
in went to Mongolia and saved a
special
copy of all the Where is John Brady?
He's still cleaning up.
He he went to Mongolia and he found
a a copy of the Kangyur, 990 books of
Buddha that never left the room.
And he he he he scanned it. His team
scanned it and they saved it.
And that book's name is tem tembangma.
What's tembangma?
Yeah, you're not allowed to take it out
of outside the threshold of the door,
you know? And he found it and he he
saved it.
Tembangma, okay? So this is temba
temba damna means right in front of your
front steps
is a medong, okay? Medong means uh
a big fire pit, okay?
It You know, like quicksand?
Pit You walk through the swamp. You see
in the movies
and the guy suddenly sinks in the sand
and he uh
And it's called quicksand, okay?
Uh but there's another kind of quicksand
that's made of fire.
And it up on top it looks like normal
ground.
But when you step on it, you fall into a
big barbecue pit
like for a cow or something. Somebody
tried to kill the Buddha that way.
You know, somebody tried to kill learn
Several people tried to kill the Buddha.
Some Several people tried to assassinate
the Buddha
cuz they didn't like him.
And one day they invited him to a
to like go on for a walk, but they
prepared a big uh fire pit.
And they were hoping he would fall in,
but I don't know, he walked over it and
he said, "My feet feel
really comfortable right now." Something
like that.
Uh
So, if you have a meadow just outside
your
door, right?
But, you're thinking about Highway 417,
you can save 6 minutes or Highway 37,
you could have saved in the third right
lane, you could have really got
So, your mind is on some
the highways in Los Angeles,
but but there's a thing outside your
door that could kill you.
You know, 1 in from your door,
there's a thing that can kill you,
but you're thinking about the highways
and how to get to Ventura a little bit
faster, okay?
Okay? What's that an example for?
Tathagata
So, people are talking about tantra all
the time, secret mantras. Geshe La,
teach me the secret mantras. Don't waste
my time with lamrim.
You know, I want to know the secrets of
Amitabha, how to go to the paradise of
the angels, like Highway 317
to the angels, you know?
And they don't realize that Dinanga
Shamba
thinking about this life, Amazon,
Facebook,
you know, it's like a fire pit outside
your door, you know? It's right there
all the time. It's going to kill you.
And you're worried about Amitabha,
you know, mantra or some secret
teaching, you know? But, you got
something inside your head that's going
to kill you.
Which is thinking about this life,
thinking about things you want this
life. Oh, I just need a little bit
better car. Everybody needs a little bit
better car, okay?
Jigme told me to tell you that the
You did tell me. The the Prius story
that she smashed her Prius, right?
Somebody gave her a new car.
And then she smashed it. And the the
next part of the story is she got a new
big SUV.
And she can drive all the way up the
Diamond Mountain Road with no problem.
So, actually it was a cool karma. Okay.
Uh
So,
people are always looking for some super
secret
thing, and they have a bomb in their own
head, okay? Called worrying about, you
know, do people know I'm a good
meditator? Did they notice in the yoga
class that I did a handstand today?
You know? And then that that ruins their
life. But, they're thinking about some
tantra thing or something like that,
okay?
The thing that's right here you didn't
take care of, and your mind is on
something that's 100 miles away, okay?
Duh.
Uh
So, that
feeling that you would like people to
notice how what a good Dharma person you
are,
it destroys your practice, and it's like
a chains, okay? It chains you, okay? It
prevents you from progress.
So,
and all of those problems come from
not doing death meditation. If you do
death meditation every day, you won't
have those problems, okay? You won't
have that bomb in your head.
Uh
I'll tell you the meaning of the goose
and the fox and the weasel later when I
figure it out.
Okay.
Anyway, it's related to the fire pit and
the highways, okay?
It's supposed to be
That's supposed to be the meaning of it.
I don't know why. Okay, here we go.
Shipa.
Uh
This is the fourth of the six problems,
okay? I don't know who's keeping track.
I also don't know what came before.
But,
maybe Jenny will tell us later or
something. We're on the fourth problem,
okay? We had three problems already.
I think the first one was if you don't
think about death meditation, you won't
think about Dharma. I think that was the
first one.
Second one, if you don't think about
death meditation, you won't
Huh?
You
won't practice today?
What's the third one?
Oh, yeah, you practice, but it's it's
polluted
by Oh, does anybody know I did a
handstand today?
Were they watching me?
Okay? All right. Now, here's number
four.
Dribble and then then don't join you me
me.
Uh
You may practice, but you won't practice
with a lot of
enthusiasm, okay? Like you won't be
really excited about it, okay?
Like this.
Did you do your meditation? Yeah, I did
my meditation.
Did you do your book? Yeah, I did my
book.
Did you do your yoga? Yeah, I didn't run
away when John Brady started to do the
hard poses. I stayed there.
You know, but there's no uh excitement
about it, okay?
Then you go to a movie and you're like,
You know, then you have to meditate and
you're like, "Oh, man."
Okay, I'll meditate, you know?
If you think about dying a lot, you
start to think meditation is sexy, okay?
All right? And it gets very interesting
to you, okay? So, right now,
you know, we practice, but it's like
pulling teeth, they say. I don't know.
It's like, "Yeah, okay, I'll meditate."
Some people are just so, what do you
call it, responsible?
They meditate every day, but they're not
like
hungry for it, you know? It's not like
the most exciting thing in their day.
They're like,
you know? I asked somebody what's the
definition of yoga, they said, "The
thing that stands between me and and
lunch."
The thing that stops me from reaching my
lunch is called yoga. He he
So, uh
If you don't meditate on death,
then maybe if you're a good person, you
can force yourself to meditate, you can
force yourself to do yoga.
You can force yourself to do your book,
but it's it's kind of like feels like a
obligation.
You just I have to do this, you know?
And if you're a good person, you will
keep doing it, you know? Just cuz the
lama told you
you have to do it, then you okay, I'll
do it.
But,
really you're more interested in what
what you're going to do after that,
okay?
So, if you think about death a lot, then
meditation gets exciting.
And yoga gets to be exciting.
Going to the old folks home and becomes
exciting, okay?
Like it feels cool. It's like listening
to good music or something, okay?
If you don't think about death, you
won't be excited about your practice.
And sooner or later you will break down.
Your practice will break down. Cuz if
it's boring for long enough,
you'll just stop one day. You get too
bored, okay?
People like you and me, we get into John
Brady's yoga class,
and we start looking at the clock after
10 minutes.
The clock in John Brady's yoga class
stops every half hour
for 20 minutes. I'm looking at the
clock, it's not even moving.
He's doing pose after pose.
It's some kind of special clock in the
in the cafeteria.
And it's not moving, you know?
And
Okay?
Then you just get tong che. Tong che
means you feel tired, you know? In the
middle of the yoga class, you're like,
"When is this going to be over?" you
know? Or in the middle of meditation,
you're like, you know? You keep looking
like you're meditating like this, right?
You're going like
Yeah, maybe the clock is broken.
Okay? That's like you get tired really
easily, okay?
But, then somebody says, you know, you
want to go to a movie, and you're like,
"Yeah."
You know? Like in the morning you felt
tired and bored, and then they say, "You
want to go see Star Wars?" and you're
like, "Yeah."
Okay.
And the problem is kun means
uh you weren't thinking about your
death, okay? If you think about your
death,
then it's really sexy to do some
meditation, okay?
Cuz you can take that with you, and you
can't take anything else with you, okay?
The the the dress you bought on Alibaba
last week,
somebody's going to throw it out.
If you die today, someone's going to
throw it out.
But but if you meditated today, you get
to take that with you, okay?
So, it's better. It's cooler. If you
think about your death all the time,
then those things are nice. Um
So, the next three meditations,
uh let's talk about them. Number seven.
Okay?
Number seven. Number seven I chose a
lady she's on a train I think but she's
doing her book. Okay, she's doing her
vow book six times book. Okay?
And she's happy to do it. Okay? She's
really thinking about her vows.
Uh because she's doing death meditation.
Okay? So that death meditation makes
practice daily
uh easy. It makes it easy to practice
every day. Okay?
I don't know. It's like playing guitar
or
I don't know.
You just have to do it every day. That's
all. You otherwise nothing's going to
happen. Okay?
So I don't really care if you're
interested or excited or doesn't matter.
You have to do it every day. You you
won't get any big result. Okay? Just a
little bit.
Just a little bit every day. You know,
put that app on your phone.
Do do like three five minute sessions.
But do it every day. Same with yoga. If
you don't do yoga every day it's just
going to always feel uncomfortable
forever.
You know, if you do a little bit every
day it starts to feel good. Okay? So
practice is just like that. Okay? You
can't brush your teeth once a week.
Okay? It doesn't work like that. Okay?
Your mouth is going to smell funny.
Okay?
Dharma
You just got to do it every day. Okay?
For the rest of your life. That's all.
You're not going to have a vacation.
Okay? It's just part You have to breathe
every two minutes.
You have to do Dharma every day or
nothing happen. Okay?
You'll always feel guilty and it'll
always be half-assed. Okay?
All right.
So you have to do your death meditation
every day. And then your practice gets
very regular. And then you get results.
Then you get nice things happening.
Okay? And you get hard. Your mind gets
hard. Your body gets hard.
You know, you become a Dharma tough guy.
Your mind gets really strong. Okay?
Okay.
Then there's a Geshe called Karagpa.
And he was practicing in a small retreat
cottage. So if you want to know the name
for retreat cottage, it's here. It's
called Dukhang. Okay? Dukhang. Sida
building.
Sida
Sida house.
Like where you're going to achieve high
realizations. Is In Tibetan they don't
call retreat cabin, they call it
realization house.
You know, which what number is your
realization house?
You know, in Tibetan the word for
retreat cottage is realization house.
Okay? Dukhang.
Then this Geshe
I don't know if you have this kind of
plant in China. I don't know.
In In Mexico I saw one it's called
Moneta I think. Coin.
It's a little vine.
And it tends to grow everywhere. And
sometimes they have uh
thorns on them.
I have it in my house. I have climbing
roses and they like to climb.
And they have uh thorns on them. And
then sometimes they grow across the
door.
And it's a big hassle. Every time you go
in the door it will scratch you.
And you know, so you cut it.
Then this was so busy practicing that he
didn't have time to cut the
thorn bush that grows across his door.
Every time he went outside he got
scratched. But he didn't have time to
cut it cuz he was too interested in
meditating. He said, "I'll cut it
tomorrow."
Then he didn't cut it to Every day he
didn't cut it. Okay?
If you delay your practice on a single
day, you will delay your practice every
day and you will die before you start to
practice. If you delay your worldly
stuff every day like, "Okay, I will
order the pink shoes with the green
inside. But I'll do it tomorrow."
You know, cuz today I got to do my
meditation. But definitely tomorrow I'll
go on Alibaba I'll get those shoes.
And then tomorrow you're like, "I got to
meditate. I'll buy the shoes tomorrow.
Okay?" So you have a choice. You can
delay your meditation forever and die
like that.
Okay?
Or you can delay your Alibaba purchases,
your Amazon purchases.
Just do it do delay it one day. And then
the next day you're like,
"I'll order it on Friday cuz I got I'm
meditating to I'm busy today. I got to
do my yoga."
Okay? And then finally when you come to
the end of your life, you won't have the
green shoes. Pink shoes, whatever.
But you'll have your suitcase will be
ready to die. You see what I mean? So if
you're going to delay something,
delay all those stupid things you have
to do. Okay?
All the men in the room you can tell
your wife
Geshe Michael told me not to do little
stupid things around the house.
You know, like fix the faucet or fix the
toilet or
He said that can wait till tomorrow.
You know, do your meditation.
And then the next day you you delay it
again and then
It's okay. You will die and the faucet
will still be leaking but you'll be
ready
to die. Okay? Got it?
So I gave all the men permission not to
do any housework. Okay?
That's what I do.
No, you got to do a little house You're
supposed to clean before you meditate,
right?
So you can do like 10 minutes of
fix the faucet or Okay?
Your house will be okay.
had uh
What's Milarepa mean?
Yeah, it's a special kind of white
cloth.
It looks like a towel. Indian people
wear it.
It looks like uh they call dhoti, right?
It's a piece of white cloth like this
long and this wide and you just tie it
around your
waist. I tried to wear it in India but I
didn't know how to
keep it from showing other things.
And finally I gave up.
Uh but Milarepa just wore that, you
know.
And like every Tibetan meditator he had
a tsampa tsampa tsampa gema.
What's tsampa?
Andriana.
Yeah, Tibetan
uh
cereal.
Okay? She makes it for me almost every
day.
It's uh monks like to have it because
it's pre-cooked. You just add hot water
and you can eat it and you can go to the
debate ground and
you know, it's super food.
It's super healthy and uh
it takes 1 minute to make it. You just
go like this and
then you
If you have too much work to do you just
And so every monk has a little bag they
carry on their belt. And it's a little
bag of tsampa.
And uh it's like fast food and it
doesn't
Some monks eat that the whole Geshe for
15 years they'll eat just tsampa cuz
they're too busy.
So Milarepa had a tsampa bag
and he had his little white cloth. And
then they started to get torn.
You know, because of why?
He used to hang out in the nettles.
The thorn green thorns.
It's actually very healthy for you.
It's good for allergies.
I got a big bag.
Uh but I didn't open it yet.
I was too busy.
Uh
but uh
he used to eat just nettles. Cactus.
Soup. He made a soup out of green cactus
and his skin got green.
And uh he didn't have time to cook.
And then his tsampa bag got torn. He
didn't have time to sew it. And his
his little towel got torn.
And he didn't have time to sew it. He
was too busy. Okay?
This is tsawa. You can tsam long This
long Those of you studying Tibetan,
okay? La not a long on long. So
generally long means to raise up or to
ask for something. But this long means
to have time.
Uh long ma tsu means I didn't have time.
Okay? I didn't have time to tsam. Tsam
means to uh
to sew something. Okay? There's a tantra
called tsambo.
There's a special tantra called the
tailor.
Someday you can learn it. Okay? Uh long
ma tsuwa. Gye zor zhe ba shin du rang re
kyam mi ta pa te na If people like us
really think about our death,
le ga she na mi tsem ba gye jo la dog
tsen we will slowly give up our other
tasks in life.
And we just kind of drop them cuz you
don't have time to do both, okay? Like,
I don't know.
You can't do Facebook and have a good
time at practice. I'm sorry. I don't
think so. You can't do Facebook
regularly and have time to meditate and
you know, you can do Facebook once in a
while, but to be if you really check
Facebook all, you know, for like 25
minutes or
45 minutes a day, you can't you don't
have time to meditate. So, you decide.
Do you want to see people's stupid
little videos
or do you want to
have a good death? You know, you decide.
Okay, you can't do both. You don't have
time to do both. Facebook is
unbelievably stupid.
Okay, I'm sorry, okay.
You don't you won't if you die suddenly,
you won't regret that you didn't read
your Facebook today.
Okay, but you will regret that you
didn't meditate today, okay? It's easy.
The choice is easy.
It's just so meaningless. Most of the
stuff online is just totally silly and
waste of time. Really bad waste of time.
Okay.
You might as well read You know what we
do in three-year retreat? You know it's
one of the favorite thing for three-year
retreat and is to read the cereal boxes.
And uh
any kind of box like any kind of
cuz you don't you're starving for
anything.
So, you spend like
if you're doing the retreat with
somebody else, you're fighting over the
cereal box.
You know, I want to read how many how
many calories in
and uh
cuz you're so like hungry for doing
wasting time, you know.
Okay, so
finally we told people just cross out
all the
anything written on the box of food,
cross it out, you know, cuz we we were
spending like an hour a day reading
them.
Uh
so, like gherkin, sal
leg a shin a mitzva so slowly you will
get behind on your Facebook posts
and you'll get ahead on your meditation,
okay? You you can choose which one you
want.
Uh duration Nobody looks at my Facebook
anymore cuz I I posted like once 6
months ago
and then I posted again like 3 months
after that and then then I just haven't
had time.
Uh
doctor tension ju
duration shumba map draw sing sing. Say
draw sing sing.
Draw sing sing.
Means, "Ooh, I get to meditate. Ooh, I
get to go to job ready yoga class. I'm
so lucky."
Okay, it's like that. You'll be excited
if you do death meditation, okay? It'll
be like
so cool to have some time to
to do some practice, okay? If if your
death meditation is good, you should be
hungry for meditation and yoga and stuff
like that.
Scott, what How
How long they going?
65 Yeah. 60
Okay, no break.
You came late.
We had the break already.
Okay, problem number five. What was
problem number four?
You won't have any enthusiasm. You won't
think it's fun if you don't meditate on
death, okay? Your practice. Number five.
Napa rang ni mar rumba che pe ni me ni.
Uh
This is a really important one, okay?
What's the picture in your meditation
book? What's the picture for number
eight? What's going on in that picture,
number eight?
What's happening?
The guy is complaining to the lady at
the coffee shop that his cappuccino
doesn't taste right.
Okay?
He went to the coffee shop. He ordered a
cappuccino.
And I don't know, it's too hot or it's
too cold or there's too much sugar or
there's not enough sugar and he's whiny
whiny person. "I don't like the
cappuccino.
It's too cold or it has too much sugar
or it took too long for you to make the
cappuccino." Okay? If you don't meditate
on your death,
you will become a whiny person.
Okay, everything will start to bother
you,
okay?
There's people who eat organic, vegan,
you know,
and they just bother other people all
the time, you know. Someone gives you a
cookie and you're like, "Is it not
gluten-free, sugar-free? Is it turbinado
brown sugar?
Was Was it baked under 300° in a flat
oven?
You know, and then
you just become a whiny pain in the
butt, you know.
Okay, so
if you just meditated on death
and someone gives you a cold cappuccino,
you're like
Okay, it's okay.
You know, everything's okay if you're
going to die this afternoon.
Okay, your mother calls you up ring ring
ring ring. You're like, "I love you,
Mom. I'm dying this afternoon, okay?"
You know,
your boss says you're stupid. You're
like, "I'm dying this afternoon. I don't
care.
You know, you didn't do that job fast
enough." I said, "Well,
maybe tomorrow."
If you know you're going to die today,
you're so patient with other people, you
know, you have so much
I don't know what you call it.
You let things go.
If you're going to die today, you let
things go. If you're going to die,
why why should you complain about the
cappuccino, you know?
Or somebody pushed you in the food line
or someone's
fell asleep in the bathroom and the jets
of a cappuccino
You know, one day I stood there for like
45 minutes and I found out somebody
locked the door and left and closed it.
And I was waiting for like 45 minutes,
you know, and
and uh
finally I knocked. I realized there's
nobody in there.
But you don't get upset about stupid
small things if you just did your death
meditation, okay? All right?
And if you don't think about your death,
then every little thing can bother you,
okay? Every little thing will bother
you. If you're going to die today, who
cares?
Okay, who cares?
You know, I don't know.
You lost one of your socks and you're
going to die today.
Okay, I can do without the sock, you
know.
Okay.
All right.
Uh
so, rang ni mar rumba che pe ni me. If
you don't think about death meditation,
you can become a pain in the ass whiny
person, okay? That's called mar rumba
che pa in Tibetan, okay?
You become like a pain in the butt
person.
Chi wa ma dana che dila she che shine.
You're so attached to every little thing
in this life.
Uh send me dung du pe che pe ni so che
pa la chak dam mosam. The minute
somebody
looks attractive to you, you want to own
them and you want to control their life,
okay?
And the minute somebody says something
negative you to you, you hate them
forever.
Okay, but if you're going to die this
afternoon,
you know, you see some pretty boy and
you're like, "Yeah, okay.
Good luck, man."
Or your boss calls you stupid. You're
like, "Yeah, okay, whatever."
People who just did death meditation are
really good at whatever.
You know, okay, whatever. Okay, chak dam
mong. Chak dam mong. What's chak dam
mong? What three animals are chak, dam,
and mong?
Chak dam means uh I want that boy today.
That's called the attachment, right?
It's the
rooster.
In the wheel of life, okay? Dam
is anger, you know. He said he called me
stupid.
Then you're snake, you know.
He called me stupid.
If you just did death meditation,
somebody calls you stupid, you're like
Huh, okay.
What the you know.
Okay, all right. And mong, what's mong?
The pig, yeah, stupid.
Stupid, okay.
I didn't get a good cappuccino. I'm
going to die this afternoon. So, let me
give the waitress a hard time. Let me
tell her how stupid she is. Let me plant
a lot of seeds to go to the hell realms
just before I die.
Okay?
Like if you're going to die today,
you're not you're going to be very
careful what you say and what you do
because the seeds that you do on the day
that you die could come up faster cuz
they're they're right in front of your
mind, okay?
So, if you might die this afternoon,
it's important not to make any small
stupid seeds like complaining about a
cappuccino, okay? Cuz you don't want to
die with that one in front.
Probably you'll be born in a Dunkin'
Donuts
serving bad coffee to people.
Okay?
So, don't make stupid little seeds if
you're going to die today, okay?
Which means you can never make stupid
little seeds cuz you don't know if
you're going to die today, okay? Got it?
Okay, top of the top of the taking
English and so hassling other people, so
arguing with other people, changing my
room and my sheer
power.
You know, being unpleasant to other
people.
If you don't do your death meditation
every day, you might get a going mat
means uh
black eye.
Somebody will get irritated with you and
punch you in the head. You get a black
eye, okay?
Mat going mat means uh
everything from a
a damage on your head to on a, okay? Uh
done my number to be so
DJ Kundo Pumbache, so not doing death
meditation is bad for next life and it's
bad for this life because it makes you
petty. So, in English, there's a word
petty. Petty means uh
you get offended about small things.
You get angry about small things. Oh,
there's too much salt in my noodles, you
know? That's called petty.
You just worry about small stupid
things, okay? If you're doing death
meditation, you won't be like that,
okay?
Dharma people should be like
have a wide tolerance for all kinds of
stupid behavior by other people, you
know?
That this person just dumped
I don't know, soy milk in my coffee.
You say, "Okay. All right, I'll just
drink it. Don't worry about it, okay?"
Dharma people should have a big
Somebody puts ketchup all over your, I
don't know, Cheerios and you're like,
"Okay."
Whatever, okay.
Okay? This You don't complain about
stuff cuz you're going to die today, you
know? I don't care.
When they cut my stomach open, they'll
find ketchup and Cheerios together.
That's okay.
Okay.
All right? Okay.
Number six, okay?
Let's do a meditation, okay? Let's do a
meditation tonight.
Have you been petty recently?
Did you complain about the noodles in
the
Yesterday, I was sitting with somebody
at dinner and they found a piece of
garlic in their noodles and they
mentioned it like six times.
And I was like
you know, it's okay, man. You know, you
die with garlic in your stomach or not.
It's all right, you know?
Okay?
So,
was I petty in the last few days, okay?
Like, did I complain about stupid small
things that don't matter if you're going
to die today, okay?
All right?
See if you were whiny or complaining in
the last few days, okay?
And then
think about death and then think how is
how important was that?
I didn't get enough sleep two days ago,
okay?
But, you know, you might have died on
the way home, so it's okay. You die with
sleep or you die without sleep, it's
about the same.
Okay? Ready?
Oh, I feel jet lag.
You're going to die today.
Okay. It's okay.
Ready?
5 minutes, okay? Just do it yourself.
Are you complaining about stupid little
things and uh
Put your death on it. Compare it to your
death, okay? Here we go. 5 minutes about
whiny Gushy Michael.
50 + 50
Okay, please come back to your breath.
Three slow breaths.
Okay, good.
Let's do some question and answer. You
have a microphone
up there somewhere?
We'll do like I don't know, 20 minutes
of question and answer if you have any
questions.
About anything. Anything is okay.
It's up to Nick. Okay.
Thank you, Geshe-la. You're welcome. Um
I have these questions uh these
questions for a while about you
mentioned to uh
when you pick an object from a for a
meditation, stay with it for
two or three weeks.
And
usually my meditation looks like uh
you know, preliminaries and tongue len
and the lama the lama's eyes and death
minute. So,
and mindfulness, you know, shamatha. So,
is it
wrong or should I change?
No, that's okay. If it's going well
and if it keeps developing and getting
deeper, then stick with it. Okay. Uh if
it starts to get dry
and uh
stick with it a little bit longer and if
it's still dry, then switch to another
object. Okay. So, it could be longer
than a few weeks. It could be a few
years. Okay.
Okay. It's a good question. By the way,
somebody asked me uh I guess I'm not the
person to ask, but um
how do what's the karma to lose weight?
So, just go to India, get an airplane
ticket to
to Mumbai
and drink water everywhere.
And uh
No, that's one method.
Uh the other method is the four just do
the four steps, okay? Some people have
trouble with their eating, okay? Like I
I can't control my eating.
I made my la- my lamas they were sick.
They said, "I want some
I feel like a cinnamon roll."
So, I looked up a
cinnamon roll
what do you call? Recipe?
I never made them in my life and I found
a good recipe. It looked really good.
So, I made them. There were 18 of them,
I think.
Mama got one.
Anyway,
uh
if you uh
you can use the four steps, okay? Number
one, I want to control my eating more
carefully. I want to try to control
myself. I don't want to go on food
binges, you know, and just eat 17 sweet
rolls.
It's pretty amazing.
And uh
number two, uh
find somebody else who has this problem,
right? Find somebody else.
Uh I can mention I think she won't mind
uh Mandy Chen in Taiwan.
And uh she had a big overeating problem
and it really bothered her.
And she used to uh she couldn't stop
eating.
And then uh she found a thing called uh
Food Addicts Anonymous. It's called FA.
It They use 12-step program.
And uh so, she has to help somebody else
with their overeating problem.
And
uh
she looks great. She She's She doesn't
overeat anymore. She can control her
eating very nicely. She looks really
beautiful.
And she decided to do it for other
people for the rest of her life.
She's She's introducing FA to Taiwan.
She's the first organizer in Taiwan of
FA organization, you know?
And that's such a smart idea if you
don't want to overeat. So,
number one, decide I don't want to
eat uncontrollably anymore. Number two,
find other people who have the same
problem. Number three,
help them 1 hour a week.
And then number four, be happy about it
before you go to bed. This is the real
way to stop
eating problem. There's no other way.
If you do a diet and it works, it's
because you did the four steps and you
did it and you know you did them, okay?
Uh so, whatever seems to work, it's not
working.
What works is karma.
So, if you want to control your eating,
then help other people, okay? Then in
American culture, I don't know China or
Mexico uh
Germany, but in American culture,
if you want to make someone happy,
you buy them chocolates
or you give them uh cupcakes for their
birthday or
you know, like in we honor people with
bad food. This is American
No, it's just uh
our parents taught taught us that, you
know, if you're a good kid, I'll give
you a cookie, you know?
So, we think if we have a friend
and we want to honor them, then I will I
will bake you some cookies or I will buy
you some special chocolates from
what's it called? Lindt and something.
I don't know. Ger- Germans have 14 kinds
of unbelievable chocolates that nobody
else has. Lindt Lindt.
I went to Tokyo. There's a Lindt shop.
It ruined my afternoon.
Uh
Then uh
Okay, so if if you want to make the
karma not to eat poorly, don't give your
friends bad food, okay? If you want to
honor your friend, make them a nice
vegan
you know,
someone gave me a vegan
tart last night. Gel say.
That was delicious
even though it was healthy.
Okay, so uh if you want to
treat your friends, give them something
healthy. And and make something
beautiful. It doesn't mean you can't
You can go in your kitchen and you can
work for an hour
and make some kind of really tasty
healthy thing.
And then the karma of that is that you
won't be so attracted to bad food, okay?
So, don't don't do this thing where you
buy people cookies or stuff like that.
It's not You're not helping them.
Somebody started a rumor in Europe that
I like chocolate.
And uh
I actually nowadays I throw it out, you
know? I I accept it. I give a big smile.
And then at the airport, I just throw it
out, you know? Cuz to give it to my
friends is also not good. You see what I
mean? Like if I bring it home and give
it to my old lady, which is what I used
to do,
it's just going to hurt her. So, the
best thing I can do is just throw it
out, you know? So,
okay?
Next question.
Thank you.
Thank you, teachers. Uh thank you for
teaching us
so that we will not fall down like to
the hell, but is there a way to bring up
our parents after they die, like get
them to heaven? Yeah, good good
question.
Uh
Is
So, we are learning ways not to go to
hell realm in this life. Uh
by the way,
when we teach Kamalashila next week,
one of the nicest things are about level
seven,
eight DCI level seven,
I think one of the nicest things is
called uh
Dor Lam Su. It means uh
when someone teaches you emptiness with
the pen,
you know?
Haha. Let's do it.
Uh
just answer, okay? Don't think too much.
What's this thing?
If a small dog comes in here, what will
they do?
Does the dog see this as a pen?
Does the human see it as a pen?
Who's correct, the dog or the human?
Mm. Then if I leave this thing here and
all the people go to have dinner
and all the dogs leave also and Tim is
the last person out and he closes the
door and there's nobody left in here. At
that time
is this a pen or a chew toy?
Yeah, nothing and that's Kong Sheng.
That's emptiness. Emptiness isn't
anything else. It doesn't mean close
your eyes, everything's black. It
doesn't mean everything is illusion. If
you think that I'm going to hit you in
the face with my illusion.
And uh
It doesn't mean nothing's good and
nothing's bad. Those are all super
stupid ideas. Shin de kupa, okay?
Uh
That's Kong Sheng. Nothing more than
that.
When the dog's not here, when the
human's not here
it's just something. It's not anything
yet, okay?
Then the person comes back in the room.
And they reach here and they look at
this thing. In that moment, what does it
become?
Yeah, it becomes a pen again. Why?
Because a seed opened in their mind. At
when they walked in the door the seed
didn't open yet. And they came closer
and closer and closer and when they
first saw this thing in that moment a
seed opened in their mind, karmic seed,
and a small picture comes out and it's
made of light. And if you meditate every
day one day you will see it, okay? One
day you will see it. Your mind is
karma, the way karma opens is it's seeds
are opening in your mind
and little pictures are coming out. The
pen doesn't come this way.
The pen comes this way. Little pictures
are going beep beep beep beep beep beep
beep.
It's like a video, you know? Little
pictures are coming out of your mind,
okay?
The word in in Buddhism for a person who
doesn't understand reality is this way
seer.
Surtong. Surtong means this way seer.
They think the pen is coming this way,
okay? Oh, that's a pen and I'm
it comes that's called that's the
synonym in Buddhism for a stupid person.
This way seer.
Okay, they think everything's coming
this way. When their husband yells at
them, they think
it's his fault. He come he want to yell
at me. They don't think he's coming from
them, okay?
Every stupid person you ever met with a
direct reflection of you.
I'm sorry.
Some people say, "I don't know why I'm
surrounded by stupid people."
They were all like
Okay? Then anyway, so who put the seed
for the pen in my mind?
I only you can put a karmic seed in your
mind. Only you can do. How did I put a
pen seed in my mind?
I gave a pen to somebody else. When my
hand opened
and the pen came into their hand
that
image of my hand opening, it made an
impression on my mind, okay? Like that.
It came into my eye
and it made an impression on my mind,
okay? Look.
See, there's a mark, okay? In a few
hours that be That's called a samskara.
And in a few hours it becomes a vasana.
Okay? That's a duche.
That's a impression and a few hours
later it becomes a mental seed.
Okay? And then you have a seed for pen
in your mind.
And immediately it starts to double
every 24 hours, okay?
Why are we talking about that?
If someone gives you that explanation,
you cannot go to the hells after you
die.
Okay? If you understand that explanation
one time
strongly
uh you cannot go be animal after you
die.
Okay? You reach Tushita, it's a special
level.
Level path number two.
Level level two level two, okay? Second
part of level two. You understand the
pen.
If you really understand the pen, you
cannot go to
you cannot go down after you die, okay?
That's like
good advertisement for level seven.
Yeah. Just come hear the pen one time.
If you really understand it and and keep
that understanding, you cannot
it's impossible even if you want to to
go down after you die, okay?
Now, what about people that we love who
don't want to listen to the pen?
Uh my father was like that, you know?
And he was a nice man
but he wasn't interested in Dharma, you
know? And uh he was a good man.
He didn't like to go to church. He
wasn't against the church, he just
didn't want to go.
And uh he wasn't interested in Dharma.
Then he got cancer.
And then I want to help him.
Uh
So in Buddhism and same in Catholic,
same Christian, if you clean your bad
karma just before you die
then uh
probably you won't go down, okay? So if
you can do a good confession
just before you die
uh
it will help you not to go down, okay?
So
in the Christians, Catholic, they have
very good custom.
When the person gets in a car accident
you know, the ambulance will come and
they will say it's too late.
And then the policeman will call the
priest and say, "Come fast to the car
accident. He's dying. Take his
confession."
You know? And then I don't know, they do
something on your hand and
the priest says, "Okay, thank you for
confession." Then you die.
Then uh
probably you won't go to a bad place,
okay? So my dad, he's dying of cancer.
I know he fought in the Second World
War.
Uh he was very young and he killed many
people.
And uh
then I
I thought, "Oh, he's dying, you know? I
I have to
he has to do confession, but uh
he won't do it. He doesn't believe in
the priest, you know? So
But real confession means you regret
something and you agree not to do it
again, okay? It's called shartum.
Shaktum. Shak means confess. Dum means
agree not to do it again. That's a real
confession.
So I tricked him.
He was dying. I said, "Dad, do you
remember you told me what you did in the
war?" He said, "Yeah, yeah." I said,
"Wasn't that terrible?" He says, "Yeah.
I killed many people." Then I said,
"Would you do that again?" He said, "No
way. No way." Then he died the next day.
Okay? So try to
get them to talk about the big mistakes
they made and uh
if you get a chance uh
at breakfast table, tell them about the
pen, you know?
In a way in not in a
missionary way. In America we have some
Christians they knock on your door
and they grab you and they you have to
believe and you're like
Not like that, okay? We shouldn't be
like that. Buddhist people should be
cool, you know?
We should trick people.
You know? You wouldn't do that again,
Dad? No.
Okay? Like that. But we don't We're not
allowed to bother people with our
religion. That's
that's why you do this mandala before
the class. I'm not allowed to teach you
unless you ask me.
Okay? I'm not allowed to bother you,
okay? Okay?
All right, good question though. So try
to get them to
clean. The best way to teach people
in your family
is to be so happy
and so successful
and so nice
that they say, "What are you doing?"
You know?
Okay? If you're unhappy and unpleasant
then it doesn't matter. You say, "Oh, I
went to Arizona." Why? You You study to
be more unpleasant?
You know?
Okay? Like if suddenly you're very happy
and your your life is really beautiful,
then of course your sisters or your
parents are going to say, "What are you
doing?" You know?
I was in a car with a guy in Ireland.
He's in our group in Ireland. His name
is
Marwan.
Not Marut, Marwan.
And he's Lebanese. He's you know, he
grew up in a Muslim country.
And uh
I was in the car with him one day. He
was driving me and his little daughter
was in the back seat. I think she's like
5 years old.
And
he says, "This is my teacher, Geshe
Michael." And the daughter said, "Why
you make daddy meditate all the time?"
And then uh daddy was embarrassed, you
know? And daddy says, "Well, you know
uh
daddy has to meditate every day. Why
daddy has to meditate every day? Cuz
daddy gets angry.
Why? Cuz cuz daddy didn't meditate. If
daddy doesn't meditate, he gets angry,
remember?
Did daddy get angry after he started
meditating?" Then she goes
"No, daddy didn't get angry after he
started meditating."
You know? Then she said, "But could you
just meditate for half an hour instead
of an hour?"
Okay? But it means that even the
5-year-old noticed some change in her
father, okay? So uh
the best way to
influence your family is to be super
happy and super friendly and super cool.
Then they'll ask you what what
are you taking some drug or
Then you can say, "Yeah, it's called
meditation."
Okay? All right. One more question? Any
more question?
But if you push your family and bother
them,
they will do the opposite.
They will say, "Okay, you know,
Buddha
you know." And they will do something
bad. So, don't push. Don't push too
hard.
Just be a good example. Okay.
Thank you.
Um I have a question about this
morning's teaching. You were talking
about the Lotus Sutra
and
the men, the dogs, and the gods, and the
Buddha having this ability to bank
his karma.
So, I get a little confused
after studying that, you know,
everything's coming. Yeah, is it I Yeah,
it's okay.
is it Does it mean that the person who's
meditating will never go hungry? Does
that person
Is Does it mean that they are
at a certain level of realization of
emptiness and
Yeah. It's a good question.
Do they have to be an Arya for
Yeah. Okay. Cuz it sounds like
in that story, and he's quoting three or
four sutras where Buddha said the same
thing.
I take my extra karma and I did dedicate
it Noah. I dedicated Gewa Di Gewa Kun
to other people who are going to be
meditating in this planet for the next
million years. I dedicate my karma
to those people
that they will never go hungry
if they practice Dharma. Nobody who ever
practices Dharma will die
from hunger.
And if they do, then I'm not a Buddha.
That Buddha said that. Then that's a
difficult to understand because
generally what we just said about your
father or your mother, you cannot give
them karma.
You can't say, "Oh, Buddha gave karma to
us, so I'm going to give karma to you,
you know. I'm going to give you my
karma."
And it's not possible. We always say
it's not possible.
Why? Because I have a dentist.
Understand?
If Buddha could give me his good karma,
I wouldn't have a dentist.
It's true. It's proof. It's ultimate
proof. You don't need more proof than
that. If Buddha can give away karma, I
won't have a dentist.
But I do.
So, it must be impossible. Now, so how
can Buddha bank
good karma for everyone who's going to
meditate after that? We have to say in
Buddhism in the in the law of karma,
it's like the blind man who got cured by
Jesus, right? And
he thanked Jesus. Thanks Thanks for
making me see. And Jesus said,
"Your faith may have have made you
whole, you know. It's your faith
created the cure, not me. Okay? Your
faith gave me the power to give you
sight." You see? So, if you
honor Lord Buddha, if you believe in
Lord Buddha, then you can you can get
the extra karma
and you will never be hungry. So, I
think you have to interpret it as saying
a person who meditates
with faith
in Lord Buddha will never go hungry.
Okay?
Something like that. Because your faith
creates the karma to get to get food.
Okay? It's not Buddha cannot hand you a
hamburger.
Big Mac.
But if you have faith in Buddha and you
go to do a retreat, you you won't die
from hunger. Something will the food the
Big Mac will roll down the highway
to your retreat cabin.
Uh but it's it's being drawn by your
faith and not by the Buddha's power.
Okay? Really.
Okay? It's your faith in the Buddha
which creates this the seed for food.
Okay? It has to be like that.
Otherwise, I wouldn't have a dentist.
And I do. And he loves to
cut. Okay?
Next question. It's a good question.
It's a good question.
Maybe one more
question.
By the way, and then some Christian
people told me, "So, you don't believe
in God, right?
You don't believe there's a
a person who can help you.
Don't you feel lonely?
You know, like we have God. When we have
trouble, we can pray to God, you know.
But you you don't believe in a God, so
you know, when you have trouble, what do
you do? Don't you feel kind of lonely?"
And then I say, "No, we have Buddha, you
know." And they said, "But Buddha can't
help you."
And we say, "Yeah, but if we if we have
trust in Buddha, that karma
helps us.
And and when you pray to your God,
we believe Buddhists believe that's
that's okay. That's possible. Because
you believe in their God and because you
follow what the God said and you don't
hurt other people,
then God can help you.
And we believe that. Like Buddhist
people accept your God.
We believe there's such a thing. You can
call it karma, but we don't say that to
Christian people.
You know, what you call God, we call
karma. But it's the same thing.
If if you are a nice person, God will
help you.
And you can call it karma or you can
call it God. I don't care.
I don't care.
You know, so if you believe in that
person in the sky called God,
and if you believe God wants you to
follow the 10 Commandments and don't
hurt anybody, be nice to everybody,
and you follow that, then of course good
things will happen to you. And then that
God will exist
because you made them.
Okay?
Okay? No problem.
Thank you, Geshe-la, for your teaching.
Um I have been working in Herbalife for
18 years and I nearly make made a big
success. Uh but in the last before 2
years ago,
I got stuck. Then I started to use the
method you taught us and
and it's getting better.
Uh I I use it for myself and in the
team.
Then my way to like attract clients,
make sales is to post things on
Facebook. And I have to use it every day
to post something and to attract people.
Yeah. And what you just said really
confused me because
Uh yeah. So, what can I do? Yeah, okay.
It's a good question. And then she's
also a
like a
teach people how to lose weight. Yeah.
Like he's also a coach for that. Okay,
good.
She's also a coach for that.
Okay.
When I say Facebook, what I mean is I I
looked at mine today.
I looked at mine this morning. I never
post anything. Never. There are 5,000
people on my uh
Facebook thing. And sometimes it just
disturbs me
because they're showing people got in a
car accident or somebody got eaten by a
shark or
you know, or just this person can beat
up this person with kicking and punching
and
you know,
many people
my friends, people I know, they're
they're putting stuff like that on
Facebook just because it's strange.
Or, you know,
I don't know. Amazing. Look, this guy
kicked this guy 34 times and finally the
guy fell down. It's so amazing.
You know, and a lot of people, I don't
know.
It really disturbs me. So, I'm talking
about that. If you can use
Of course Buddha will use Facebook.
Uh
uh
Hello. Hello. Uh she need to attract
attract people. She need the attention
from the people. Yeah. Yeah. That's
fine.
thing? Yeah. Not bad. Not bad. I mean,
if you use it to make people healthy, if
your motivation
is uh
I will show this uh Facebook
video about the cute little kid because
then people will buy something make them
healthy,
that's fine. That's great. Buddha uses
tricky things all the time.
I'm sure Buddha will use Facebook.
You know, but but you have to be careful
why you're using it. Okay? If you're
just gossiping
about, you know, I don't know, this
chicken had two heads and
he lived in No, many many many things
like that in Facebook.
Uh then it's just waste everybody's
time. But if you are trying to attract
people to make them healthy,
then you should do more Facebook.
And you should do LinkedIn and all those
other things, Twitter
and uh
WeChat, WeTalk and
You should use everything. Okay.
Okay.
Yeah, it's your motivation. Okay? And um
Just be careful with wasting your time I
mean looking at other people's junk.
It's just junk. I have some friend, he's
a good friend of mine. He always put up
the video of the people uh doing uh
What do you call MMA or
MMA, just hitting each other
and uh trying to kill each other and
and I'm really surprised cuz he's a nice
person.
And um
and then I start to watch it cuz he put
it on my Facebook and
Okay, one more.
Here's a guy.
No, it's okay. It's okay.
Last question. Thank you, Geshe.
Uh you said uh how karma works and like
in the in the DCI you told you taught us
uh our all the karma we have planted is
like uh the plan waiting in the
in the airplane airplane waiting in the
line, right? And it will ripen
according to the time when we planted.
Yeah, in accounting they call it FIFO,
FIFO.
First in, first out. Yeah, but just now
you said before we die,
the bad karma just ripen right away,
right?
Yeah. So it's just the It's a balance.
It's a balance. It's a good question.
Okay? Uh
Any karma that you plant with strong
emotion can go ahead of the other
airplanes.
And also any karma which is very fresh
in your mind
temporarily it can go ahead for for like
half a day or something. Okay? So if you
just had a big fight with your friend
but you were nice to your mother for 6
days
and you die suddenly
And the bad karma the big fight is in
front. Okay? Just for a short time, then
it goes back to that back. Okay? So
it's very important for example in the
in the Buddhist scripture
it says uh never freeze the body of a
dead person.
Try to wait for 3, 4 hours at least.
Okay? So in America there's a law
when the person die in the hospital,
they have to go in the refrigerator
within half an hour or something. And uh
but for Buddhist
uh we're supposed to try to keep them
out of the refrigerator because
they're not quite dead yet.
Then they feel cold and they say, "I
need fire. I need fire." And they go to
the hell.
They go to the fire hell. You see what I
mean? Uh
There's famous story somebody was dying
and they they the last thing they saw
was a a beautiful elephant.
And they're like, "I want to be a
elephant."
Then they're born as a elephant. Okay,
so anything that's very fresh
uh we have to be very careful about
people while they're dying. Like we
shouldn't be noisy. There shouldn't be
people
You know, everybody should be quiet.
There should be some quiet mantras.
Everything should be peaceful. All the
family should be support them.
And and everyone should be quiet and
peaceful and
try to help them to go quietly. Okay?
Cuz if you make some big noise or if you
startle them or
if they suddenly see someone they didn't
like for 20 years
then that there's a danger that seed
will come up
by accident. And the last seed in this
life is very influential in the next
life. Okay? You can spend your whole
life nice person
then if the last thought is angry
it's a big danger. Okay? Like that. So
So we have to be very careful of the
last few hours.
Uh just to make it peaceful and quiet
and things like that cuz that seed
temporarily it goes ahead.
It's a good question.
Yeah.